<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Robert Danger Winters</title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://robertwinters.nl/tags/data-vault/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Rob Winters</author>
    <copyright>2015 Rob Winters</copyright>
    <updated>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Vault Loading Automation</title>
      <link>http://robertwinters.nl/2015/04/2015-04-10-data-vault-source-automation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Rob Winters</author>
      <guid>http://robertwinters.nl/2015/04/2015-04-10-data-vault-source-automation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Note: These posts on data vault automation are an in-depth discussion of functionality described &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/RobWinters1/data-vault-automation-at-the-bijenkorf&#34;&gt;in a 10 Mar 2015 presentation on the Bijenkorf&amp;rsquo;s DWH architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we began our vault rollout, one of the initial challenges we faced was the disparity of relational systems to work with: MySQL (various versions), Oracle 11g, Vertica, etc. While heterogeneous replication is an ideal solution in this landscape, the majority of servers were partner hosted and so actual code/feature deployment on the machines was not possible. As such, the easiest solution available was to deploy code generators based on metadata derived from our staging environments. This approach offers a number of advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easy integration of new tables:&lt;/strong&gt; Rather than building new ETLs or modifying code to add new tables from existing sources, we can integrate the new information automatically by deploying the DDL in the DWH&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resiliency against source changes:&lt;/strong&gt; In the event that the source system adds additional columns to the source, changes referential integrity, etc, ETLs are not impacted. Only INT-&amp;gt;VARCHAR changes is source data models cause issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automatic full vs incremental loading:&lt;/strong&gt; Using the last timestamp off our ODS view layer allows the scripts to only pull the new records from the sources; in the event that nothing is currently in the ODS, the engine will automatically pull everything.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;engine-workflow:133b05d48047fcbc0514da03bd26193c&#34;&gt;Engine workflow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;{{site.URL}}/static/DV_Automation.png&#34; alt=&#34;High level data vault workflow model&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>